Guide to the Ralph Emerson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Ralph Emerson Papers
1807-1871
RG 285
Yale University Divinity School Library
7
(19 boxes)
The Ralph Emerson Papers (1807-1871) primarily document the professional work of Emerson as a Congregational clergyman and faculty member at Andover Theological Seminary. Letters to and from his wife Eliza are included in the correspondence.
Emerson, Ralph, 1787-1863
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1787 August 18 Born in Hollis, New Hampshire
1811 Graduated from Yale College
1814 Graduated from Andover Theological Seminary
1814-1816 Tutor, Yale College
1816 June 12 Ordained (Congregational)
1816-1829 Minister, First Congregational Church, Norfolk, CT
1829-1853 Brown Professor of Ecclesiastical History, Andover Theological Seminary
1829-1853 Minister, South Congregational Church, Andover, MA
1842-1853 President of the Faculty, Andover Theological Seminary
1853-1858 Minister, Newburyport (MA) Congregational Church
1858-1863 Lecturer, Chicago Theological Seminary
1863 May 20 Died in Rockford, IL
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School Collection, 2017
Scope and Contents
The Ralph Emerson Papers (1807-1871) primarily document the professional work of Emerson. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: journal, correspondence, student lecture notes and essays from Yale College and Andover Theological Seminary, lectures, essays, addresses, sermons, publications, and notes on readings. Included in the correspondence are letters to and from his wife, Eliza.
The majority of sermons are in a shorthand system probably devised by Emerson. There is no extant key to the system, although it might be possible to compile a key by analyzing a letter of Emerson to Charles Prentice, November 7, 1829, of which there are two, one in shorthand and one in longhand.
Arrangement
Series I. Journals
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Notes, Lectures and Writings
Series IV. Sermons
Series V. Publications
Series VI. Notes on Readings
Series VII. Financial Records.
Congregationalists -- New England; Emerson, Ralph, 1787-1863; Andover Theological Seminary
- Journals, Series I
  - Entries, 1808 January 1 - 1811 September 12 (Box 1)
  - Entries, 1811 November 25-27 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    (in Daybook I, student papers, Andover Theological Seminary, p. 10)
  - Entries, 1812 January 17 - June 26 (Box 1)
    (in Daybook II, student papers, Andover Theological Seminary, p. 37)
  - Entries, 1829 October - December (Box 1)
  - Entries, 1846 August 18 - October 18 (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences of myself and others (autobiographical essay), 1855 September 20
- Correspondence, Series II
  For a complete list of letters, see the original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Undated correspondence, primarily to Eliza Emerson from Charlotte and Mary Rockwell, No date (Box 1)
  - Letters to / from Ralph Emerson and Eliza Emerson, 1809–1837 (Box 1)
    Correspondents include Rockwell family, Pierce family, Leonard Woods, B. Wisner, First Congregational Church, Norfolk, CT.
  - Letters primarily to Ralph Emerson and Eliza Emerson, 1838–1853 (Box 2)
    Correspondents include Rockwell family, Pierce family, and others.
  - Letters primarily to Ralph Emerson and Eliza Emerson, 1854–1871 (Box 3)
  - Association: Letters: Charles Rockwell to Mrs. Charles Rockwell; from Pontiac, MI (May 18, 1846) --- to D. P. Colburn; from --- (Box 19)
- Notes, Lectures and Writings, Series III
  For a full list of titles, see original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Student papers
    - Yale College
      - Lecture notes, 1809–1811 (Box 4)
        Including "Chemical lectures", "Hebrew Grammar", and lectures by Dr. Timothy Dwight and Professor George Edward Day
      - Essays, 1808-1811, no date (Box 4)
        Titles include "On profanity", "Comparison between a spendthrift and a miser", and essays on God, on Yale students, on human nature
      - Notebooks, 1807–1811 (Box 4)
        Including notes on sermons preached at Yale
    - Andover Theological Seminary
      - Daybooks 1-9, 1811–1814 (Box 4)
        All but #9 have sustained fire damage. Including notes on lectures by Professors Stuart, Woods, Park
      - Dissertation: The greatness of the preach[er]'s task. (for examination in the department of sacred rhetoric), 1814 September 28 (Box 4)
        Fire damaged
  - Course documentation
    - Church history lectures (Box 5)
    - Pastoral theology lectures (Box 6)
    - Questions for classes, 1828–1849 (Box 6)
  - Essays
    - Essays arranged by title, No date (Box 6)
      Titles include "Epitome of history", "Evils against which a pastor & his people should especially guard after a season of awakening", "General report presented to the Peace Society in the Theological Seminary, Andover, at their annual meeting, Aug. 1832", "Jerome's account of monkery in Egypt"
  - Addresses
    - Addresses arranged by date, 1810–1860 (Box 7)
      Titles include "Valedictory oration on energy of character", "Ecclesiastical history as an element in female education"
- Sermons, Series III
  For a full list of sermon texts, see the original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Fragments and undated sermons arranged by text, No date (Box 7)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1813–1816 (Box 7)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1816–1817 (Box 8)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1817–1819 (Box 9)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1819–1820 (Box 10)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1821–1824 (Box 11)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1824–1842 (Box 12)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1843–1853 (Box 13)
  - Dated sermons and sermon notes, 1853–1862 (Box 14)
- Publications, Series IV
  - Articles
    - Fragments (3), No date (Box 14)
    - Can there be a wordless thought? (for the New York Observer), No date (Box 14)
    - A history of Congregationalism, No date (Box 14)
      (first draft prepared at the request of Dr. Sprague for insertion in his Annals of the American Pulpit, of which only an abstract was published)
    - History of the rise of the Protestant system, No date (Box 14)
    - Obituary notice of the Hon. William B. Bannister of Newburyport, Mass. for the Congregationalist, No date (Box 14)
    - A plea for the unmutilated version of the Bible as made by King James' translators, No date (Box 14)
    - Review of Jesse's History of the House of Stuart, No date (Box 14)
    - Review of Palfrey's History of New England, volume 1 (2 folders), No date (Box 14)
    - Verbal inspiration, No date (Box 14)
    - On the origin and commencement of the Reformation; from Planck's Protestant theology. American Biblical Repository 9 (1837): 332-358; 10 (1837): 104-141, 253-297 (Box 14)
      translated by Emerson; (proof sheets with some corrections in RE's hand)
    - On provoking our children to wrath. The Mother's Magazine and Family Library 11 (1843): 183-189, 193-202 (MS) (Box 14)
    - The early history of monasticism; from the original sources. Bibliotheca Sacra 1 (1844): 309-331, 464-525, 632-699 (Box 14)
      (4 folders--proof sheets, with corrections in RE's hand)
    - Early history of monkery in the church--from original sources. (rough draft of above), 1844 (Box 14)
  - Books
    - Wiggers, G.F. An historical presentation of Augustinism and Pelagianism from the original sources. Trans. Ralph Emerson. Andover: Gould, Newman & Saxon, 1840 (Box 15)
    - Life of Rev. Joseph Emerson, pastor of the Third Congregational Beverly, Ms. and subsequently principal of a Female Seminary, Boston: Crocker and Brewster, 1833. (Box 16)
      Incomplete manuscript
  - Proof sheets
    - Proof sheets of articles by Emerson [?]: Church history, Review of the works of Nathanael Emmons, D.D., No date (Box 17)
- Notes on Reading, Series IV
  - Notes on reading arranged by title, No date (Box 17)
  - Unitemized notes, No date (Box 17)
- Financial Records, Series V
  - Bills and receipts (Box 18–19)